Bernard Elbert Gray Papers MS020
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Bernard Elbert Gray Papers
1927 -- 1983
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Gray, Bernard Elbert
MS020
0.75 Linear Feet
Arrangement
This collection is organized in one series.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains biographical information, correspondence, 1950-1981, memorial/obituary, 1982-1983, and technical papers, 1927-1948. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence to and from Bernard Gray in his capacity as Head Class Agent for 1911 and a collection of technical papers written in connection with the Asphalt Institute.
Biographical / Historical
Bernard Elbert Gray was born in Andover, Massachusetts in 1888. He graduated from Tufts University with a B.S. in Civil Engineering in 1911. During his summer vacations he worked for the Massachusetts Highway Commission. After graduation, he joined the Commission full time as an Assistant Division Engineer engaged in building roads and bridges. From 1916-1918 he worked for the U.S. Bureau of Public Roads which he rejoined (after a year in the military during World War I) as Senior Highway Engineer supervising Federal Aid projects. Starting in 1921 he worked for the West Virginia State Roads Commission in various positions and advanced asphalt technology.
Gray went on to become one of the world's leading experts on highway engineering. He was very active in the Asphalt Institute, an international trade association of petroleum asphalt producers, manufacturers and affiliated businesses. He wrote many technical papers in the highway engineering trade press, addressed those in the highway engineering field at industry conventions, and among other posts served as President of the Asphalt Institute from 1947-54 which he had joined in 1930 as Highway Engineer. Gray was a former director of the American Road Builder's Association, a trustee of the Automotive Safety Foundation, a member of the Highway Research Board, the American Society of Engineers, and the Vermont Engineering Society. Gray received an honorary degree from Tufts University in 1935. Bernard Gray died on July 24, 1982.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Gray, Bernard Elbert; Alumni collections
- Bernard Elbert Gray, papers, 1927 -- 1983; MS020.001; 0.75 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains biographical information, correspondence, 1950-81, memorial/obituary, 1982-83, and technical papers, 1927-48. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence to and from Bernard Gray in his capacity as Head Class Agent for 1911 and a collection of technical papers written in connection with the Asphalt Institute.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged as found.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Biographical information, 1927 -- 1983; MS020.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1950 -- 1969; MS020.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1970 -- 1981; MS020.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Memorial/obituary, 1982 -- 1983; MS020.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Technical papers, 1927 -- 1948; MS020.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Technical papers, 1927 -- 1948; MS020.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Technical papers, 1927 -- 1948; MS020.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Technical papers, 1927 -- 1948; MS020.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Technical papers, 1927 -- 1948; MS020.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Technical papers, 1927 -- 1948; MS020.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Technical papers, 1927 -- 1948; MS020.001.002.00002 (Box 2)